Did October 7 change you?
It changed a lot.
It changed a lot. First of all,
we know how much it costs to be alive.
That's the first one.
And then,
it changed the way of thinking how to live here.
I published a book three or four months before
the war and I called it, in Hebrew,
"Chayim al HaGvul", it's a double meaning,
it means "Living on the edge" or "Living on the border",
"Near the border",
and it's optimistic. It's an optimistic a book.
Because we always said that
we are living in 95% of heaven,
and only 5% of hell.
The hell is the times that we have to
leave the house for a few days for a few weeks.
We did it sometimes ago, but not for two years.
We learned how to live out of the house
and we hoped to get (back) in.
And it has changed the way of thinking about our place.
And it changed what we are thinking about our neighbors,
because because before the war,
most of this area,
most of the kibbutzim were very activistic.
For example,
I can tell you that I was one of many people who were
going to the border and taking children to hospitals,
Palestinians and their children.
And did it.
I didn't think that I'm bringing the peace.
I'm not the beauty queen that
"Bringing the peace for all",
"All over the world".  I thought that we are
helping to make a new generation.
And that the new generation will be able to talk.
Not to do peace.
There will be no peace in our generation.
Maybe for the little ones,
they will (have peace), but not in our generation.
We thought that we are making something that
will make them talk with us,
make the children of Gaza talk with my grandson,
or with my child.
And what we saw after October 7th,
that there is no uninvolved people on the other side.
Everyone is involved,
because the one who came here to kill and rape
and stole things from the kibbutz,
he's involved, of course.
But the others?
They were cheering their heroes,
or they took parts of bodies of our children,
or they hide hostages.
At last, they didn't tell
their neighbours "Don't do it!"
It's a little part,
but they are involved.
I told the people who came here after the October 7th,
they told me that
they can not do it because of Hamas,
and so and so.
I told them two things.
First of all, if it's (only) Hamas that did it,
then we are doing good to the world now,
that we are killing the Hamas people.
But...
the people in Gaza, if the...
When I'm not agree with my government,
and I'm not,
I'm going to the street.
I'm telling all the world what I'm thinking about
my government.
They have to do it too. They have to go and talk.
It's a risk, but I'm taking a risk too.
So if they want to live like me,
they have to change their mind.
And...
Even though
I've told you before that there is no uninvolved people,
I'm sure now and I knew it before:
if we want to live good here in Israel,
in Kfar Aza,
they have to live good over there.
We failed. We tried to do it,
but we failed. Someone else has to do it.
The Arabs the Europeans,
the American,
the people with the money. I don't know who.
But they have to create
a new Gaza
that the people in Gaza will have something to lose
if they do it again.
If they will do October 7 again,
they will have something to lose.
They're losing now their homes,
but
they don't care now.
They will care in a few months,
when peace will be here,
the ceasefire will be here.
So if the world wants
to do a good life in this area,
and if they want to do money,
most of the people want to do money...
The area of of Gaza,
the city of Gaza and the others,
it's beautiful places, we can do there a lot of things.
The world can do
a lot of things that bring them a lot of money.
But they have to do it. We failed.
We tried.
I told you
I was going
to the border to take children (to the hospital).
And other people did,
they buy and sell something, to Gaza.
They have great strawberries
in some of the areas of Gaza.
And if the world if the world,
if Humanity so much doesn't want the people in Gaza to be killed,
so do it. You can do it now.
It's the right time and in the right place.